[SPEAKER_01]: So, let's start with the question.
[SPEAKER_01]: Does meditation lead to the cessation of craving?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or does one need to understand the cessation of craving in order to meditate?
[SPEAKER_01]: Anatta,
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, why is it that only an arahant is free from craving?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's the argument that people would make.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if, for example, somebody becomes a satipaṭṭhāna, gets the right view, understands the Four Noble Truths, they're not fully free from craving until they become an arahant.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, but then there is a distinction between being fully free from craving, which is the āt, and actually rightly seeing that craving is the origin of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right, so then, so, but does that mean that when you have understood that craving is the origin of suffering, your practice, like you cannot help but do the practice with craving?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, that is now the next question.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, when someone has rightly understood for himself these four noble truths, which is like craving is the origin of suffering, then it is based upon that insight that basically the Noble Eightfold Path arises, which is the foundation of the way the Buddha discusses, let's say, meditation.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that would be the distinction there.
[SPEAKER_04]: But then, to say that that one's making progress along the Noble Eightfold Path based on craving, would be contradicting that very insight which is the Four Noble Truths, namely that craving is the origin of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because if you have understood the cessation of craving, actually, which is the understanding of the Sotāpanna, then why would you keep
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, quite the contrary.
[SPEAKER_04]: It seems to me, then, your understanding would be that you want to avoid acting out of craving, which is how you make progress along the non-virtual path.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, so then, what if then somebody says, well, but how can you make effort?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if you just give up all craving, then you just don't do anything and you just sit there, kind of dead.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, that is how it would seem for someone, then, who has not
[SPEAKER_04]: Let's say, fully understood, these four noble truths, to the point that the Noble Eightfold Path arises.
[SPEAKER_04]: They cannot help then, it seems to me, but think in terms of craving.
[SPEAKER_04]: But, what we could do, is take that as a starting point, let's say, the ordinary person perspective, take a peek, let's say, beyond the fence, so to speak, and try to find out what are then, if it's not craving,
[SPEAKER_04]: That is the determining factor for progress along the Noble Eightfold Path.
[SPEAKER_04]: Can we then clarify...
[SPEAKER_04]: Which factors allow that noble disciple to become an arahant?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but before we get into that, just to to show kind of the the fallacy of the view that I just mentioned, well, if giving up craving means that you don't do anything and you're just there not not practicing at all, then how is it that an arahant continues to... like, how is it that the Buddha was able to teach
[SPEAKER_01]: Who knows how many thousands of discourses.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, you know, make effort to have his dhamma be understood.
[SPEAKER_04]: And, and, you know... Ah, so you're asking how can there be effort without craving?
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, because people would say, no, no, but how are you going to give up craving?
[SPEAKER_01]: When you're not an arahant, if that means that you won't be able to practice towards arahantship.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how can there be effort without craving?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is another question.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, so, because that's exactly as you said, from the point of view of an ordinary person, they cannot separate intention from craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: It seems like it's necessary, necessarily bound up together.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, unfortunately then, you know, most approaches to meditation today, kind of, instead of pushing people to develop their view and see that those things can and should be separated, it's like, no, no, no, it's okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just need to find a better type of craving, a better type of delight, a better type of, you know, attachment, that's going to, like,
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, progressing and refining your attachments until you have no attachments.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Meanwhile, you keep justifying just that same craving and attachments in the name of refining it.
[SPEAKER_04]: And as long as you keep justifying it, you're not abandoning it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The thing is, you know already that it's unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you know already that you're acting out of attachments.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whatever attachment is left there for a noble disciple, that he doesn't understand, or that he hasn't seen for himself, it's there because he hasn't seen it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not because he's telling to himself, oh, yes, I know that it's there, but, you know, because for now I'm a noble disciple, I won't deal with this.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's precisely because he's not aware of it, that he hasn't dealt with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, no, these people are saying, no, no, I'm fully aware
[SPEAKER_01]: That these whole jhānas and meditation and everything is just a light in, you know, in sensations and stuff even.
[SPEAKER_01]: And yet, you know, it's fine because, thanks to this, I don't give in to the sensual coarse things in the external world that I used to give in to.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, but that's quite quite a problem, because in this kind of view, like, that implies that the object is the problem, and as long as you keep refining the object, that's fine, because eventually the object becomes so refined that craving is not there anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that totally overlooks the fact that craving is an attitude towards the object.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, like, if... actually, if you maintain the view that the object is a problem, freedom is impossible, because there will always be an object.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and that's pretty much why, you know, in... with this kind of view, you know, the... they would try to kind of lay out the path, like how it's gonna pan out in the end.
[SPEAKER_01]: But very rarely do you actually see that they say, no, no, I know for myself that that's going to be, you know, that this craving is going to disappear eventually.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's kind of taken on faith.
[SPEAKER_01]: That by just refining it and refining and refining it, it's going to fade away eventually.
[SPEAKER_01]: But like...
[SPEAKER_01]: Very rarely would you be able to see someone who says, no, no, I know for myself, that by taking this route, craving has actually faded away.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's because that's not how it works.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you cannot... like dividing something by two, or by whichever number,
[SPEAKER_01]: An infinite amount of times still leaves you with something.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as you said, it's the attitude of craving, the attitude of expectation, the attitude of wanting that needs to be put in question.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's by recognizing that as the issue that you would abandon craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that then leads to the next point.
[SPEAKER_01]: What did the Buddha say is the origin of craving, in the most fundamental sense?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it just an energy that's kind of there on its own, kind of like primary to everything else, or does it have a kind of fundamental basis?
[SPEAKER_01]: Feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: More fundamental.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's the point that's overlooked there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Craving is there, and everything, in the whole mass of suffering, the whole pācī-sampāda factors, is there because ignorance is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, it's not a matter of like, oh, craving is there because I haven't practiced for 20 years, like, destroying this energy that's there little by little.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, if you were to stop being ignorant today, you would have no craving today.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, because craving is like...
[SPEAKER_01]: Ignorance creates a space for craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when that space is not there, then... that's the only way to... like, you have to remove the space where craving kind of finds an entry.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like... deal with the craving itself and try to diminish it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's with the arising... with the complete fading away of ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which was the root of everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything else gets destroyed like a kind of a series of dominoes or something.
[SPEAKER_04]: In the context of the planetary dimension.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's where... because usually, yeah, when it's... because kind of the
[SPEAKER_01]: common denominator, most of the time, is the management.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, what you're really confusing with craving, or what you think is craving, is more like, how do I refine my feelings?
[SPEAKER_01]: How do I make them smaller and smaller, until, you know, there isn't craving because you have managed your feelings so well, not because you have actually uprooted the liability to craving by abandoning ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: So,
[SPEAKER_01]: Having said that, what does it mean to...
[SPEAKER_01]: Understand the cessation of craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, is that, poof, an experience that you had one day, and, oh, wow, I saw the cessation of craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, it's like, like this, how they call it, fruition experience or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you get it once, and then, if you have that kind of memory or whatever, that's your stream entry.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, and then you've got all the review knowledges based on that.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, before you know it, you're probably lost in the commentaries.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you get Alzheimer's, then everything is gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you forgot the experience.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's a bit of a dubious take on the whole matter, it seems to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what does it mean, then, to understand cessation?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, actually, the suttas would say... we did a talk on that one already, where it says the two types of meditation, the tamed horse and the untamed horse, and it says that the tamed horse is like just watching the hay,
[SPEAKER_01]: And then the untamed horse asks himself, what does the trainer want me to do today?
[SPEAKER_04]: That's... it's totally wrong.
[SPEAKER_04]: The untamed horse is watching the...
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, later on, when it talks about what does it mean, like the thoroughbred's meditation, as it says there...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: It says, it's not dependent on air, water, fire, on earth, water, fire, air.
[SPEAKER_01]: on this what's seen, heard, cognized, dependent on anything, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, it says at the end that even the gods don't know on what basis that meditation proceeds.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, that kind of hints at the point of
[SPEAKER_01]: That cessation, cessation of craving, how that is the right meditation, not that that's the result that, like, later on that's magically going to happen to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to have that recognition of how to meditate like the thoroughbred in order to be meditating right.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what does that mean then?
[SPEAKER_01]: Cessation of craving, cessation of dependence, dependencies, cessation of
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, kind of practically speaking, the way I understand it anyway, will be that whenever I see myself craving for something, will be to actually restrain myself from acting out of that very craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because as long as I'm acting out,
[SPEAKER_02]: I feed this same attitude and then the cessation is impossible because I am feeding it by acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, in order to see the cessation, I have to kind of allow it to happen in a way that
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't act out.
[SPEAKER_02]: Otherwise, if I'm acting out, it's kind of impossible.
[SPEAKER_02]: It kind of implies that I keep rolling with it, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, so, is it just to stop giving in to it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you just stop giving in to it and that's it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Or is it and to not try and get rid of it, no matter why, of not acting out of it?
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm not trying to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because you can also go to the other extreme of denying it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Trying to, yeah, imply that it shouldn't be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is also really great.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, but then...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in order to give up something that you were acting out of, do you need to have something else motivating you?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, do you need to have a prize at the end?
[SPEAKER_01]: To say, like, oh, if I give this up, I will receive this reward.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: What is there already is a broader context.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, what is there already is, for example, the fact that your body is... that you're... that you're sitting, or you're standing, or you're in a posture, or that you are breathing, or...
[SPEAKER_03]: So, there is already a context there.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not... not in time,
[SPEAKER_03]: There is already... you find yourself in this... you find this broader context already there.
[SPEAKER_04]: That you do not need to achieve in the future.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, meaning... That is absent from craving, if you...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, meaning...
[SPEAKER_01]: If you... like, you cannot say that in order to give up one drug, you need to take up another drug.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, for sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just see that the fact that, as you said, you're already subject to this body, you're already confined with this experience that's not in your control, that in and of itself means that giving into craving is not a good idea.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not because, like, I'm gonna get this other reward, which I won't get if I act out of craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just, no, in and of itself...
[SPEAKER_01]: Craving is not beneficial.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, strictly speaking, this whole idea of, like, I need to refine it with the next thing and with the next thing... No, like, you recognize your drug is is harming you, and then, based on that recollection, that this is not for my welfare, you give it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not on the basis of, like, I want this other thing that's better than this.
[SPEAKER_01]: So,
[SPEAKER_01]: That leads us then to the next point, which you sort of brushed on before.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is it that would drive your progress, if it isn't driving?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes, now we arrive at that question.
[SPEAKER_04]: If one has understood that craving is the origin of suffering, and always unwholesome, that even logically it's a contradiction to say, based on the four Noble Truths, that with craving I'm going to make the ending of craving, then what is it that propels that Noble Disciple, let's say, along the Noble Eightfold Path?
[SPEAKER_02]: Just one thing that came to mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just like, if one sees that craving actually is the root of suffering, he actually sees that acting out of craving is painful, and that recognition itself, seeing that acting out of craving is painful, is enough to not act out of craving, which makes him progress.
[SPEAKER_04]: But then, if he still accidentally slips up here or there, then what would happen?
[SPEAKER_02]: How would that be regarded for somebody who actually... Oh, shame, shame, and regret, and kind of...
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, just feel bad about it, basically.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, that's exactly it.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, when the... that's one of the factors, like, when the Buddha discusses factors of a noble disciple.
[SPEAKER_04]: I mean, there's various lists and contexts, but there are several ones that always start with
[SPEAKER_04]: This is the īri and the uttapa, right?
[SPEAKER_04]: The, let's say, the healthy shame and fear of wrongdoing.
[SPEAKER_04]: And so to say, well, to still go back to the craving, this is below me, this is low, I've already understood that it is not worthwhile, then it is that factor or that faculty which is now based on the right understanding that will prevent him
[SPEAKER_04]: From not doing it again, which is the progress.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what is actually the Buddha gave specifically about this topic?
[SPEAKER_01]: He said...
[SPEAKER_01]: He gave a simile about somebody who wants to go to a park, and then for as long as they haven't reached that park, they would still have
[SPEAKER_01]: You could say the motivation to reach that part.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once they reached it, they no longer have that motivation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So there is one thing, or let's say a group of things, that the Buddha talked about as factors of the path, that
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's a good fact.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, not specifically.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a bit of a... more of an academic question.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's the, you know, the four, quote-unquote, spiritual powers.
[SPEAKER_01]: Uh-huh.
[SPEAKER_01]: The first one of which is... Go on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Desire.
[SPEAKER_04]: Chanda.
[SPEAKER_04]: And so... Yeah, but that is... but you see the chanda is not now the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so that's the point I'm making.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, there's even a... there's even a sutta where the Buddha is saying that he's going through the jhānas, or I think Sariputra is going through the jhānas.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then he's kind of analyzing the factors of each jhāna, and all of them basically have chanda in them, but none of them have craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, eh... the point being, chanda...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, even... even an arhant, the Buddha said, even an arhant was to have chanda, because, I mean, how... how would you otherwise, you know, have any interest in teaching people?
[SPEAKER_01]: How would you otherwise have interest in going for alms round?
[SPEAKER_01]: How would you have...
[SPEAKER_01]: interest in, like, I don't know, your kuti breaks and you had to fix it or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, jhāna simply means, like, you could translate as interest or motivation, but it's not, it's not, unlike ignorance, it doesn't depend on craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, sorry,
[SPEAKER_01]: Unlike craving, it's not founded upon ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there can be chanda, even though there isn't ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, of course...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's a wholesome motivation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pretty much, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when we talk about this, like, what you said, oh, you recognize that acting out of craving is not for your welfare, you want to give that up.
[SPEAKER_01]: That would be a form of chanda.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, taking it up to the, like, beyond what it needs to be and saying, oh no, it's because I want this specific thing, this specific experience or whatever, now you're falling into craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there's even that sutta where, I think we briefly discussed it in
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, the previous talks that says... that famous verse that says, don't long for the past, don't long for the future, what is presently arisen...
[SPEAKER_01]: He clearly sees...
[SPEAKER_01]: He clearly sees unwavering, unfaltering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, in the description there, it says, if somebody is longing for the past, for the aggregates, like the way their aggregates were in the past...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they delight in that, then that's... it says... so that's running after the past.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, if somebody has a desire for the aggregates to be a certain way in the future,
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter which way.
[SPEAKER_01]: That in itself is another form of delight, craving, you could say.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, if in the present, they're not clear about, as it says, unenlightened ordinary person doesn't understand form is not self, feeling is not self, form is not self, then they're moved by things in the present.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, that whole discourse is basically saying, in order to practice rightly,
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to abandon all of these anticipations of, like, what experience you will have, what kind of... what will come after this, when I give all of this up.
[SPEAKER_01]: The goal is, right now, what is there, this feeling that has arisen, this pressure that has arisen, this craving that has arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't act out of it and don't give in to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then,
[SPEAKER_01]: If this kind of desire arises, like, oh, oh, what's going to come after?
[SPEAKER_01]: I want this, or I want that, or maybe this is... is that going to be the nibbāna that I read about in the suttas, or whatever?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's now something that's presently arisen, and if you give in to that now, again, you're acting out of craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's how you keep yourself balanced, and that's how you are basically
[SPEAKER_01]: While being effortful and diligent, you're also patient.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how there ceases to be a kind of discrepancy between those two, because, you know, for people it would seem like, oh, either I am just, like,
[SPEAKER_01]: Some sort of divine laziness which is missing the mark also.
[SPEAKER_01]: The point of diligence, but you don't overstep.
[SPEAKER_01]: You recognize there is a need for diligence, but it applies to what is presently arisen, not for you to try to get things that you don't have, even if it's experiences.
[SPEAKER_04]: Or to get rid of things that happen to be the case now, for that matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because then, as it says, well, you're moved by form, feeling, perception that has arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Trying to get rid of it is another form of taking it as mine, because otherwise
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why would you try to modify something if you know that it doesn't belong to you?
[SPEAKER_04]: Now, would you say that this is the... that this could be a description of the Thoroughbred's meditation on how it doesn't depend?
[SPEAKER_04]: Pretty much, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That you could make that connection.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the important point is to recognize that
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that in itself could be a contemplation that if somebody really kind of takes it to the full extent, obviously on the basis of training on a practical level, virtue, sense restraint, and the gradual training, that they try to differentiate.
[SPEAKER_01]: How can I have chanda?
[SPEAKER_01]: How can I have an interest?
[SPEAKER_01]: How can I have motivation for practice without it being craving?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, for as long as you don't have the right view, yeah, that will... has to seem to some extent as a paradoxical situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: But...
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, when you actually understand craving, you see, oh, well, this was redundant all along.
[SPEAKER_01]: There was no need for this.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, the chanda survives the former way of the craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, that's the entire piece that the Buddha talks about, like the seven enlightenment factors.
[SPEAKER_01]: It says dependent on cessation, dependent on withdrawal, dependent on dispassion, so...
[SPEAKER_04]: He develops and then it goes to all these factors.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, all of that already, like all the peace, the calm, the joy, all of that already depends on you giving up craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there is no other type of happiness or pleasure that can be wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's bound up with craving, it's unwholesome for the very reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So,
[SPEAKER_01]: The main thing to recognize as well is, you cannot justify any instance of craving if you're aware of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: There will be things that, inevitably, especially if you haven't trained and, you know,
[SPEAKER_01]: The gradual refinement that does happen is a refinement of the gradual training.
[SPEAKER_01]: That can be spoken about.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's a refinement of understanding.
[SPEAKER_04]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: Not like making the craving more subtle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, if you haven't refined that, then for sure there will be instances of craving that, even if you try, you won't have recognized them.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: The stuff that you do recognize.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if you break your precept, you don't let go.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, this is fine or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Later, I'll give it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're aware of it, the diligent thing to do is to restrain it and prevent it from... prevent the transgression from occurring.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's already a good attitude to have from the beginning.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, there's also this one discourse in the Mahāyāvādika, where it in fact says that if a noble disciple would transgress training rules, he would not leave them.
[SPEAKER_04]: If a trainee does that, he would not leave them unbroken, precisely because he now understands that you cannot break the important ones without having been craving involved.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's bound up with this, eh... with this, eh... healthy sense of, basically, shame and fear, knowing that that goes against that principle which has now been understood.
[SPEAKER_04]: You, at least for yourself, you don't want to have that, eh... situation then and during that would be a bit of a contradiction.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the thing is, there's even this sutta where...
[SPEAKER_01]: It is kind of a late sutta, and some scholars argue that maybe it came later, but the principle is perfectly sound.
[SPEAKER_01]: This grade 40 sutta that says, like, there's a right speech, a right view, mundane right view, and separate mundane right view, mundane right intention, separate mundane right intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: The curious thing is, it doesn't go all the way.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't say that there is mundane right effort and subpar mundane right effort or mundane right mindfulness and subpar mundane right mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: It stops at right livelihood.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not that you have like mundane right samādhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a contradiction in terms.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the point there being, it says, when a noble disciple is practicing right speech, practicing right action, it says, he does so with a mind that's free from defilements at that moment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the critical thing to see.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it's the liability to the defilements
[SPEAKER_01]: That a noble disciple hasn't overcome.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the third noble truth, as it's defined even in the suttas, it's the remainder-less fading away of craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's basically just that they haven't been established in that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they know the full cessation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there's even another sutta that says, what is the right practice and the wrong practice?
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, the right practice, or the right path, it says, with ignorance, activities.
[SPEAKER_01]: With activities, consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, basically, it lists the prajñāsambhāda in the normals.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's the wrong path.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the wrong path.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, the right path, it says,
[SPEAKER_01]: The path, it says, with the remainder less fading away of ignorance, there is cessation of activities.
[SPEAKER_01]: Cessation of activities, cessation of consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, that's the path.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, can we say that there is this general principle that in the suttas they also talk about development, right?
[SPEAKER_04]: Or bhāvanā, like there's many suttas which says a noble disciple develops enlightenment factors or a noble atrial path.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that it's very easy to assume that the development is always positive, going towards something, based on and so on.
[SPEAKER_04]: Whereas, the whole dhamma has this negative... Well, it's timeless.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, it's timeless, but it's got this negative prompt.
[SPEAKER_04]: Not negative in the sense that it is depression or anything.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's not an emotional connotation, but negative that it's based upon cessation, giving up, dispassion, relinquishment.
[SPEAKER_04]: And so, by not falling back into the craving, which is the positive thing, that you abandon.
[SPEAKER_04]: And by the abandoning, you make progress towards the complete cessation of suffering.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that is sort of a negative progress, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_04]: But that is the only progress from the point of view of the Noble Dhamma.
[SPEAKER_04]: But that requires now a shift in understanding those words like progress and development.
[SPEAKER_04]: in all mundane affairs, are always like, I make an effort now in order to get something in the future, and then you are already in this sort of time-bound way of thinking, which is like, may my aggregates in the future be like this, or like that, and then you're basically done.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's when the suttas, somebody would tell like a monk, tell them, oh, you should just row, because
[SPEAKER_01]: You're kind of chasing after something that takes time, while sensuality and worldly things are just available right in the present.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he would say, no, it's the opposite.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sensuality takes time.
[SPEAKER_01]: The dhamma is always presently applicable.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's important to see, then, that
[SPEAKER_01]: Meditation and...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, there's a reason why, so to say, the no boyful path is acquired by sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's important, then, to recognize the goal should be understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will only arrive at the cessation of... at the understanding of the cessation of craving, if you're trying to understand the cessation of craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whereas, the usual view is, I do this technique, I do this method, and then, by doing the same thing... As a result.
[SPEAKER_01]: As a result.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's kind of like this saying that says, like, doing the same thing and expecting different results.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a definition of madness.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: I think it was Einstein who said that, no?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're not... you might get a special result.
[SPEAKER_01]: That doesn't mean it's different from... like, it's special compared to what you're used to.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not special.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you're still within the same overall overarching view of what the practice is and what's important and what's not important.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're not... unless you're trying to understand, you're not going to progress towards understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, nobody just, I don't know, spends their time cooking expecting that that's gonna result in tomorrow being a good pilot.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, only, you know, sitting at the cockpit, messing around with the knowledge that you don't know what you're doing, eventually results in you being the pilot.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you, through trial and error, reading the suttas, making effort to contemplate,
[SPEAKER_01]: You understand what the cessation or craving is, and then you can practice meditation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because then it's just like, how do I kind of focus
[SPEAKER_01]: My energy on just developing that principle, not just on the level of keeping the precepts and stuff, but even on a mental level now, in relation to the five hindrances, even there now, I don't act out of craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that would be the right meditation, where it says, after a noble disciple acquires the seven enlightenment factors,
[SPEAKER_01]: Then he, then he can, then he has access to bhāvana, or development.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, so we should clear up that bhāvana, which means like development or cultivation, fully depends on the right view and so in the context of the suttas, strictly pertains to noble ones.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, the problem, but the reason, the particular reason for that is, now you can start to see, it's not because it's just like a kind of, like some arbitrary gateway, like, no, only sotāpannas are allowed here, you cannot pass.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because, if you don't understand the situation you're craving,
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, again, craving is not like a switch that's on or off.
[SPEAKER_01]: For as long as there's ignorance, craving is there, one way or another.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, through not understanding what craving is, any development that you try to do will be based on craving.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, and craving as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, of course, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you cannot develop
[SPEAKER_01]: Until you have kind of acquired the vision of what right development is.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: Now, can we say that that vision, and the suttas do speak about, you know, acquiring the vision of dhamma, which is just like the right view, can we say that that's nibbāna already?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, there are suttas that say that a noble disciple understands nibbāna, sees nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, because there are so many now mystical views about what nibbāna is.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, as the Buddha would say, it's the destruction of passion, destruction of aversion, and destruction of delusion.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, and because he sees that, the suttas also say he can practice the straight path.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, he's not going like this, because he knows where the cessation of
[SPEAKER_04]: But a full cessation of suffering takes place, because you understand right here and now, what is the cessation of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's not like a fruition experience, that you close your eyes, sit there for two hours, and okay, I got nibbāna again.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's whenever you're going, walking, sitting, lying down, abandoning passion, aversion and delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is what the right meditation would be as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, only then, once you have understood how to be... like, you go, as we said before, you go this way,
[SPEAKER_01]: You're acting out of craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: You go this way, you're acting out of craving.
[SPEAKER_04]: But you're also not standing still now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, inevitably, patujjana is going to be going one of those two routes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: As the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, only by understanding the middle way, which is, as the Buddha said, patijjusam upāda, only then can you... can your development not be based on craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: On giving up craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your development would not be based on... Oh, would not be based on craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the link between keeping the precepts and sense restraint and nibbāna becomes very clear with that understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, because... to the... to... like, it is a extinguishment, a quenching of...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, quite the opposite from being like you're shifting the craving, you're removing the craving in more refined levels.
[SPEAKER_02]: Instead of bringing the craving with you, you peel it off.
[SPEAKER_03]: But I think many schools of Buddhism would see that practice as
[SPEAKER_03]: Fundamentally, you cannot gradually move towards the cessation of suffering.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, either the cessation of suffering is fully understood right now, or else you haven't understood it.
[SPEAKER_04]: But if you're then going to gradually go there, that's where you take a wrong turn.
[SPEAKER_04]: So you... so... so... so... what if somebody's contemplation
[SPEAKER_04]: There might still be this pressure to envisage a future where... where...
[SPEAKER_03]: I am in the state of nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_03]: But then, you have to include that in the fact that that is present.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's impossible for that not to be right now.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Any vision of the future.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, somebody includes that as well.
[SPEAKER_04]: Which means some longing comes up.
[SPEAKER_04]: May I attain nibbāna?
[SPEAKER_04]: Which is a little bit dubious, but okay.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's also understood.
[SPEAKER_04]: You include that because that is just what arises.
[SPEAKER_04]: We just recognize that, understand that, as you just explained.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then, all there is, is what we find now.
[SPEAKER_04]: Five aggregates doing their own thing.
[SPEAKER_04]: What's the problem with that?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, are you asking, like, what the practice is there from that position?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: If somebody questions himself like that, well, then there will be the mind trying to get you to crave.
[SPEAKER_03]: Or the mind will be, at some point, dragging you towards ill will or
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not like you're in a position, as you describe, of being an arhat.
[SPEAKER_03]: There is ignorance.
[SPEAKER_04]: But we have said that, in a sense, craving involves time.
[SPEAKER_04]: And so, we have taken the route of craving, but I'm now trying to find out if we just take time as a factor, and we're just going to stay with what is.
[SPEAKER_01]: I would say that the thing is, that could easily also get it drifted into the direction of mystification.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, yes, you can... well, going back to that sutta that we just talked about, you can kind of dismiss the past, you can dismiss the future,
[SPEAKER_01]: But, in relation to the present, that's precisely where it says uninstructed ordinary person, who hasn't seen the Noble Ones, takes form itself, takes feeling itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's like the last part that you cannot really go past without the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the person can give up expectation of, like, nibbāna or whatever,
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, they would fall into the view of glorifying the present moment, of like saying like, oh, yeah, I'm perfectly content with what is there now, the present, just this, it's just this.
[SPEAKER_01]: And ironically, then, that's overshooting the mark, because now they're kind of pretending like there isn't ignorance, that everything is just fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's not the case.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: And why does that happen?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, again, because they went in that direction of development,
[SPEAKER_01]: Pretty much, instead of the direction of clarifying their views before they even try to, you know, go into these more subtle aspects of giving rise to the joy of the present moment or whatever, again, only when you have understood how to not have craving, would that thing, would any any kind of quotation of such kind be wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as the Buddha said, it's whether it's a tiny bit of experiment, or whether it's a lot, all of it smells the same way.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whether it's a tiny bit of craving that you're acting out of, or a lot of it, none of that is in the way.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, there can be craving also to just stay with what is.
[SPEAKER_04]: Just to be clear.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, everything I just described, like, it's not that if you just stay with what is, and you sort of abandon the past, and you abandon the future,
[SPEAKER_04]: That craving is only in the past and in the future.
[SPEAKER_04]: No.
[SPEAKER_04]: On the contrary, it can also be in in relation to what is.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, Ten Sutta that you were referring about, then says, and he sees with clear understanding, this has arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, he he also abandons passion for the present.
[SPEAKER_01]: He doesn't take refuge in the present, as some people would say.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, take refuge in the present moment or something.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, um...
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is kind of a contradiction in terms, because it's like, oh, I go back to the present moment, but it implies that you run away from... from where you come from, if you go back to something.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're conceiving the present moment.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, actually, I was going to bring this up before, but I forgot about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's one sutta that says,
[SPEAKER_01]: Based on craving, one abandons craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same way, it says, based on food, one abandons food.
[SPEAKER_01]: Based on... what was the other one?
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't remember the other one, but I think there was three of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it says, but then it gives a description.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't say, like, based on the no wayful path, based on practicing samādhi, that's still rooted in craving, he gives up craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: It says, here, somebody hears, such and such a person has become an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, on account of that, craving arises in him to make progress towards that state.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, when he kind of starts, in the beginning, yes, everything will be really craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's going to be visiting the Buddha, asking information, trying to clarify things.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's going to be a lot of restlessness, a lot of doubt, and all of that is craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, for that moment, that craving is kind of setting the basis for him to begin the practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, when it comes to him actually understanding the practice, if he wants to become a sotāpanna, he needs to understand the cessation of craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not saying like...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not saying like that that's just going to continue forever or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, that's what puts you kind of like in the vicinity of the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's almost faith, basically.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, if he could do it, I can do it.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, let me crave or make effort.
[SPEAKER_04]: But then, that faith needs to be upgraded.
[SPEAKER_04]: That understanding of craving needs to be upgraded.
[SPEAKER_04]: But
[SPEAKER_04]: But something is planted there, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and so, then he would, if he gets the right view, then he would understand, oh, yeah, that craving initially led me, or in order to get the right view, he would have to understand, yeah, that craving initially led me to want to practice, but now, as I said before, I need to be able to separate this craving
[SPEAKER_01]: Throw that away, and just keep the motivation for practice, keep the diligence, but without the need for that craving.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, and that is the understanding that needs to arise, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, only with understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not going to be something that happens by itself, because, as we said, the whole craving is based on ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, that's why... that's what has been taken out of context, that people just say, oh, yeah, based on craving, you abandon craving, but they don't read, like, the next part of the sentence.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, so it might be valid,
[SPEAKER_04]: Let's say, from the very beginning, that it cannot be used as a justification on the Noble Eightfold Path, nor even to get to the right view, because that is already based on understanding that craving is the origin of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, because why would you be like, oh no, I know that this is suffering, but I'm okay with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's... yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's... if truly your goal is the ending of suffering, you wouldn't have that attitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, oh, I know that this is giving me cancer, and I want...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm trying to get rid of cancer, but no, it's fine, I'll keep it there for now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, can we say that with the craving, there is an action, there is a volitional energy, whereas with chanda, it's... yeah, it's less... it's less... this action is less... how can I say...
[SPEAKER_01]: You mean the intensity?
[SPEAKER_01]: The intensity of the action?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, in the sense, although when it says that there is no more action, it just let... yeah, you find it there and...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, is there... yeah, I'm not clear about the difference between these.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, that would be a good thing to clarify.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what do you think would be, like, a good measure of... just some example of an action, when it's just chanda, and when it's just... when it's actually craving?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: How would you be able to tell for yourself?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, externally,
[SPEAKER_01]: It might look the same, like, some people might say, oh, some people even blame the Buddha, the ascetics and stuff, when he saw, when they saw him eating, like, normal food, they thought, oh, he's just acting out of craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, since you cannot measure it by the external standards, necessarily, unless the person is, like, breaking precepts and stuff, how would you be able to tell for yourself, internally, what is more, like, just chanda, and what is clearly craving?
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know, because in one sense, if you see that it's craving, you are understanding it, and so you are going more towards chanda.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: But what...
[SPEAKER_01]: Since there is ignorance... What is... what is there when there is craving?
[SPEAKER_00]: The action, the wanting, the pressure... And what is... and how is that felt?
[SPEAKER_00]: Pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in other words, when there is craving, as always, there's going to be suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the main kind of practical rule of thumb would be, if something is rooted in craving, or if you have a desire, let's say, you have an interest to do something, if that interest is infected with craving, the effect of that is going to be, if you don't do it,
[SPEAKER_01]: You're gonna suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's just chanda, then you don't do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not gonna... it's not gonna be a big deal.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there is no passion involved.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there is...
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's how you would measure the presence of passion or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, not by necessarily kind of
[SPEAKER_01]: The external qualities of the action, let's say, like how much you did or how much effort you put in, it's more like how much would you have suffered if you couldn't do it.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that is on the level of reflection.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's not that you actually need to do it or not do it.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's already secondary.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it would be based on pretty much recognition and self-honesty.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, this mind is like a trained animal.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you know, it wants to kind of get up and do something, but if you don't let it, it's not that it's going to start barking at you and stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that would be one practical way to realize, like,
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, as the Buddha would say, eating just for the sake of sustaining the body, for example, or using the lodgings, or using the robe just for the sake of the minimal survival, then that would be like, oh, you know, am I having... would I be bothered if I can't eat today?
[SPEAKER_01]: Would I be... or would I be bothered if I can't get the food that... the specific food that I want to get?
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, see, even if the answer is no, and the mind doesn't really care, that doesn't mean that you wouldn't still try to find something to eat.
[SPEAKER_01]: The point being, if you don't get anything, you're not going to suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's... that's the poems in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would say, like, the monks back in the day, like, whether he gets something in anāryānta or not,
[SPEAKER_01]: He wouldn't be affected.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: There's this line.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm not sure how accurately it is translated, but it says somewhere, he expects only what is given.
[SPEAKER_04]: But you don't know, of course, beforehand what is given.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, how can you expect it?
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's a nice way of putting it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you could say, oh, look, he went to get it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how can that not be rooted in craving?
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's because, again, it's not rooted in that external kind of qualities of the action.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's internally, how much was he emotionally invested in a certain outcome, let's say.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's where the ignorance is reflected.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you...
[SPEAKER_01]: Ignorance being, let's say, fundamentally taking things in mind, not understanding the lack of ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any suffering, to any extent, is going to be rooted in the fact that you took something as yours.
[SPEAKER_04]: Which could be, for example, this very body.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: If you take it as yours, then the whole relationship of food, which is what this body depends upon, becomes problematic.
[SPEAKER_04]: But now imagine that it is, to the extent that it can be imagined, that this body is not yours, then how does that affect your relationship to food, to its necessity, to the sensuality that is bound up with it?
[SPEAKER_04]: All those actions, all those cravings in relation to food,
[SPEAKER_04]: will undergo, let's say, radical shift, because you now see that that has only value in relation to this body, which is seen as not yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so that's where the contemplation of anatta would have a valid, like a tangible effect.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not just a philosophical idea.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's precisely in this context of
[SPEAKER_01]: Does the mind actually have these desires and obsessions still, or not?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: And with rope and lodgings is, of course, also directly bound up with having a body, because you want to protect yourself from elements, from sun, heat, animals and stuff, which is what the lodging does.
[SPEAKER_04]: Lodging is basically sort of a further extension of your rope.
[SPEAKER_04]: Your rope you have on you, but then you go into the lodging for further protection.
[SPEAKER_04]: But it's the same principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So...
[SPEAKER_01]: To the extent that you understood... to the extent that you're not ignorant about things not being yours, you will not suffer when you don't get what you want.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you try to get it.
[SPEAKER_01]: With Chanda.